Guide to the Allan Nevins Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Allan Nevins Papers,
1912-1992
Nevins, Allan, 1890-1971.
104 linear ft. (ca.40,700 items in 207 boxes; 8 oversize items; 6 record storage cartons of books).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079154
Biographical Note
American historian and editor.
Scope and Content
Approximately 12,000 letters to Allan Nevins from various correspondents including James Truslow Adams, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, Harry S. Truman, Willa Cather, Mrs. Grover Cleveland, Van Wyck Brooks, Robert Frost, Newton D. Baker, Archibald MacLeish, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Carl Sandburg, and Henry Wallace; notes and typescripts for Nevins' books including Emergence of Lincoln, The Ordeal of Democracy, Rockefeller, and History and Historians, with notes by editor Ray A. Billington; miscellaneous transcripts, clippings, newspapers, and photographs. Also, autograph letters and manuscripts by presidents, Civil War figures, financiers, politicians, and authors. There are also the Brand Whitlock World War I Diaries and letters to him by such people as Herbert Hoover, Gen. John J. Pershing, and others.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Historical Correspondence
Series II: Professional Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts, Diaries etc.
Series IV: 1982 Gift
Series V: Oversize Material
Subjects
Standard Oil Company.; Adams, James Truslow, 1878-1949.; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908.; Commager, Henry Steele, 1902-1998.; Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948.; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890.; Hewitt, Abram S. (Abram Stevens), 1822-1903.; Hone, Philip, 1780-1851.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Rowse, A. L. (Alfred Leslie), 1903-1997.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Whitlock, Brand, 1869-1934.; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947.; Cleveland, Frances Folsom, 1864-1947.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963.; Frost, Robert, 1874-1963.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965.; Billington, Ray Allen, 1903-1981.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison), 1874-1960.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; Women authors.; Women authors, American.; Poets, American.; Presidents--United States.; Capitalists and financiers.; Politicians.; Authors, American.; Autographs.; Awards.; Certificates.; Clippings.; Diaries.; Diplomas.; Dissertations.; Essays.; Lectures.; Lists.; Manuscripts.; Memorabilia.; Notes.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; College teachers.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1953 M-53 Nevins, Allan Gift
12/04/1992 M-92-12-04 Papers Mayer, Meredith Nevins Gift
Alternate Formats
Lord Bryce letters are on microfilm.
Willa Cather letters are on microfilm.
Royal Cortissoz letters are on microfilm.
Elizabeth Benton Fremont diary is on microfilm.
Gift of Allan Nevins, 1953 & 1954.
Bequest of Alan Nevins, 1971.
Gift of Anne Nevins Loftis & Meredith Nevins Mayer, 1982.
Gift of Meredith Nevins Mayer, 1992.
- Series I: Historical Correspondence
  In Boxes 1-6 of the collection
  - Adams, Charles Francis
  - Adams, Henry
  - Adams, Jane
  - Ade, George
  - Albert, King of Belgium
  - Albert I, King of the Belgians
  - Allen, Margaret V.
  - Alliot, Hector
  - Ames, Oakes
  - Anderson, Henry James
  - Arnot, N.D.
  - Arschot Schoonhoven, Guil1aume
  - Asquith, Herbert Henry
  - Astor, Henry
  - Athlone, 1st Earl of
  - Atkins, John DeWitt Clinton
  - Babcock, O.E.
  - Baker, Newton D.
  - Bancroft, George
  - Barnard, Frederick Augustus Porter
  - Barnum, William H.
  - Beard, Charles A.
  - Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant
  - Belford, R.J.
  - Benton, Thomas Hart
  - Benzon, E.I.S.
  - Birren, Joseph P.
  - Black, Alexander
  - Blaine, James G.
  - Blair, Sherman
  - Bliss, Tasker H.
  - Bok, Edward William
  - Boker, George H.
  - Briggs, William H.
  - Broat, J.B.
  - Brown, Lewellen A.
  - Bryan, William Jennings
  - Bryant, William Cullen
  - Bryce, James MICROFILM
  - Bynum, William D.
  - Cadwalder, John L.
  - Canda, Charles J.
  - Carnegie, Andrew
  - Carter, James Coolidge
  - Chamberlain, Daniel Henry
  - Childs, George W., et al.
  - Claroye, Ida B. (Mrs. W. D.)
  - Clemenceau, Georges
  - Cleveland, Grover
  - Clews, Henry
  - Cobb, Howell
  - Cockran, William Bourke
  - Colfax, Schuyler
  - Conkling, Roscoe /
  - Commager, Henry S.
  - Cooke, Jay
  - Cooper, Edward A.
  - Cooper, Peter
  - Cooper, Peter & Cyrus H. Field
  - Cooper & Hewitt
  - Cattenet, F.
  - Coxa, Cleveland
  - Creel, George
  - Crey, Marie de
  - Curzon, George Nathaniel, Lord
  - Cushing, Caleb
  - Dana, Charles A.
  - Dana, Richard Henry
  - Darrow, Clarence S.
  - Dart, Matilda S.
  - David, Sgt. Robert B.
  - Davie, George M.
  - Davis, Jefferson
  - Davis, John Chandler Bancroft
  - Davis, John W.
  - Davis, Robert H.
  - Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel
  - Denstan, Charles
  - Depew, Chauncey M.
  - Dewey, John
  - Dewitt, Charles
  - DeWolf, Philip
  - Di Wiart, Mme. Carton
  - Dix, John A.
  - Dodge, William Earl
  - Duer, William A.
  - Dunbar, Paul Laurence
  - Dunne, Mary Kate
  - Eames, Emma
  - Ebbets, William Henry
  - Edmunds, George F.
  - Elisabeth, Queen of Belgium
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David
  - Einstein, Albert
  - Einstein, Margot
  - Evarts, William M.
  - Evvard, John M., et al.
  - Ewing, W.G.
  - Fesseden, William P.
  - Field, Cyrus
  - Field, Wlater T.
  - Fish, Hamilton
  - Fish, Stuyvesant
  - Fisk, James, Jr.
  - Flagler, Henry M.
  - Flagler, D.W.
  - Flexner, Abraham
  - Ford, Worthington C.
  - Fox, G.A.
  - Frederic, Harold
  - Frelinghuysen, Frederick Theodore
  - Frémont, Elizabeth Benton
  - Frémont, Francis P.
  - Frémont, Jack
  - Frémont, Jessie Benton
  - Frémont, John Charles
  - Frémont, John Charles, Jr.
  - Frémont, Sally A.
  - Frenzel, John P.
  - Frost, Robert
  - Fuller, Henry Blake
  - Garland, Hamilin
  - Gentry, Mary (Mrs. Thomas Benton)
  - Gibson, Hugh
  - Gilson, S.D.
  - Godwin, Parke
  - Gompters, Samuel
  - Gould, Jay
  - Grant, Thomson V.
  - Grant, Ulysses S.
  - Greeley, Horace
  - Green, Andrew H.
  - Green, Anne Bosworth
  - Grenier, G.C.
  - Grosvenor, Victor Alexander, Earl of (1853-1884)
  - Guard, William
  - Guthrie, James
  - Hanna, Marcus Alonzo
  - Harison, William H., Jr.
  - Harper, William
  - Hartnell, Mary E.
  - Hay, John
  - Hay, Lucy (Mrs. Logan)
  - Hendrix, Joseph C.
  - Herbert, Hilary A.
  - Herrick, Myron T.
  - Hewitt, Abram S.
  - Hewitt, John
  - Hill, David B.
  - Hitchcock, J.S.
  - Humphrey, Hubert Horatio
  - Hoar, Ebenezer Rockwood
  - Hodgson, Richard
  - Holmon, William S.
  - Hoover, Herbert
  - Houdini, Harry
  - House, Edward M.
  - Howells, Abby
  - Howells, Mildred
  - Howells, William Dean
  - Hubbard, Gardner G.
  - Hudson, Joseph
  - Huntington, J.W.
  - Hunton, Eppa
  - Hurst, Fannie
  - Jaffrey, Robert
  - Jehay, F. van den Steen de, Comtesse
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines
  - Johnson, Reverdy
  - Johnson, Tom
  - Johnston, William
  - Jones, E.B.
  - Jones, Samuel M.
  - Jowett, Benjamin
  - Julian, George W.
  - Jusserand, Jean Adrien Antione Jules
  - Kendall, Amos
  - Kennedy, John F.
  - Kerr, Sophie
  - Ketchum, Hiram
  - Knap, Charles
  - Lament, Daniel Scott
  - Lansing, Robert
  - Lee, Arthur Hamilton, Vicsount Lee of Fareham
  - Lindbergh, Charles A.
  - Lindsay, Vachel
  - Lindsay, Nicholas Vachel
  - Lindsey, Ben B.
  - Lipton, Sir Thomas
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot
  - Lossing, Benson J.
  - Low, Seth
  - Lummis, Charles F.
  - McAdoo, William Gibbs
  - Mac Arthur, Robert Stuart
  - McClellan, George B.
  - McClure, T.C.
  - McCutcheon, John T.
  - McKain, Emma Jane
  - Marbury, F.F.
  - March, Alden
  - Marshall, Thomas R.
  - Martin, William J.
  - Masefield, John
  - Masters, Edgar Lee
  - Meade, Robert D.
  - Mencken, Henry Louis
  - Mercier, Désiré-Joseph, Cardinal
  - Merriam, Kibtie
  - Milner, Alfred
  - Milner, Alfred
  - Mitchell, Henry S.
  - Morgan, J. Pierpont
  - Morrow, William
  - Morton, Levi P.
  - Motley, J.L.
  - Nicholson, Meredith
  - Nimitz, Chester William
  - Nordhoff, Charles
  - Morton, Levi P.
  - Orendorff, S.
  - Ottendorf, Oswald
  - Page, Thomas Nelson
  - Paine, Albert Bigelow
  - Palmer, Loren
  - Peabody, Elisabeth P.
  - Pershing, John J.
  - Phillips, William
  - Pinchot, Clifford
  - Pitkin, Timothy
  - Pound, Ezra
  - Pratt, Orvill G.
  - Pritchett, Henry S.
  - Putnam, Herbert
  - Randall Samuel J.
  - Rhodes, James Ford
  - Richey-Borrodaile corres.
  - Riley, James Whitcomb
  - Robeson, George M.
  - Roebling, John A.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore
  - Root, Elihu
  - Rose, Sir John
  - Rose, Wickliffe
  - Ross, Nathaniel
  - Rowse, A.L.
  - Sadler & Sands
  - Salisbury, James Edward Hubert
  - Gascoyne-Cecil, 4th Marquess of
  - Schurz, Carl
  - Scott, William H.
  - Seelye, Julius H.
  - Seymour, Charles
  - Seward, William
  - Seymour, Horatio
  - Sherman, John
  - Silliman, Benjamin
  - Smith, Henry H.
  - Smith, Marshall
  - Sothern, Julia Marlowe
  - Sparks, William A.J.
  - Stahl, John M.
  - Stanford, Fannie E.
  - Stanton, Edwin M.
  - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur
  - Stephens, Alexander H.
  - Steffens, Lincoln
  - Stetson, Francis Lynde
  - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing
  - Stewart, Alexander T.
  - Storrs, Richard Salter
  - Strachey, Evelyn John St. Lee
  - Straus, Isidor
  - Sutter, John
  - Swan, Benjamin L.
  - Sykes, W.L.
  - Taft, Abby
  - Taylor, Fred
  - Thomson, J. Edgar
  - Thornton, Edward
  - Thornton, W.A.
  - Thruston, R.C. Ballard
  - Thurman, Allen Granberry
  - Tilden, Samuel J.
  - Towne, Charles Hanson
  - Tree, Herbert (Beerbohm)
  - Treichel, Charles
  - Tucker, Nathaniel Beverley
  - Tucker, Beverley
  - Tuthill, Anna B.
  - Underwood, John Cox
  - Underwood, Warner Lewis
  - Utley, George B.
  - Van Dyke, Henry
  - Van Meter, Lt. L.M.
  - Wallace, Henry Agard
  - Walsh, Richard J.
  - Ward, William
  - Warren, N.W.
  - Washbourne, Elihu
  - Watkins, Gora B.
  - Watson, P.H.
  - Webster, Daniel
  - Webster, Sidney
  - Weed, Thurlow
  - Weitenkampf, Frank
  - Welles, Gideon
  - Wharton, Edith
  - Wheeler, E.J.
  - White, George
  - White, William Allen
  - Whitlock, Brand
  - Whitney, Eli
  - Whitney, Henrietta F.
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf
  - Wilcox, Charles G. Finney
  - Williams, James H.
  - Williams, John L.B.
  - Wilson, Edith Bolling (Mrs. Woodrow)
  - Wilson, Henry
  - Wilson, Woodrow
  - Wise, H.A.
  - Wister, Owen
  - Wood, Eugene
  - Wood, Fernando
- Series II: Professional Correspondence
  In Boxes 18-31 of the collection
  - Acheson, Dean
  - Adamic, Louis
  - Adams, Charles Francis
  - Adams, J. Donald
  - Adams, Samuel Hopkins
  - Agar, Herbert
  - Alden, Raymond M.
  - Allen, Hervey
  - Anderson, Maxwell
  - Angell, Normal
  - Arvin, Newton
  - Astor, Nancy, Viscountess
  - Atkinson, Brooks
  - Auchincloss, Louis
  - Auerbach, Joseph S.
  - Baker, Newton D.
  - Baker, Ray Stannard
  - Bancroft, Frederic
  - Baruch, Bernard M.
  - Beard, Charles A.
  - Becker, Carl
  - Benedict, Ruth
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent
  - Benét, William Rose
  - Benton, Thomas Hart
  - Benton, William
  - Bercovici, Konrad
  - Bergman, Lewis
  - Bingham, Millicent Todd
  - Björkman, Edwin August
  - Bliven, Bruce
  - Boorstin, Daniel J.
  - Bowen, Catherine Drinker
  - Bowers, Claude G.
  - Boynton, Genry Walcott
  - Bradford, Gamaliel
  - Braithwaite, William Stanley
  - Brodie, Fawn M.
  - Brogan, Denis William
  - Bromfield, Louis
  - Brooks, Cleanth, Jr.
  - Brooks, Van Wyck
  - Brucker, William Hepburn
  - Bunche, Ralph J.
  - Burnett, Whit
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray
  - Byrd, Richard E.
  - Cain, James M.
  - Calverton, Victor Francis
  - Canby, Henry Deidel
  - Cane, Melville
  - Carmer, Carl
  - Cather, Willa S. MICROFILM
  - Chase, Mary Ellen
  - Cherne, Leo
  - Chute, Marchette
  - Colum, Mary M. (Mrs. Padraic Colum)
  - Colum, Padraic
  - Colvin, Sir Sidney
  - Commager, Henry S.
  - Connally, John B.
  - Connelly, Marc
  - Cortissoz, Royal MICROFILM
  - Costain, Thomas B.
  - Cousins, Norman
  - Cowley, Malcolm
  - Craven, Avery C
  - Creel, George
  - Daniels, Jonathan Worth
  - Daniels, Josephus
  - Davis, Elmer
  - De Voto, Bernard
  - Dewey, Thomas E.
  - Dippel, Philip Jr.
  - Dirksen, Everett McKinley
  - Dobie, J. Frank
  - Dos Passos, John
  - Douglas, Paul H.
  - Dreyfuss, Henry
  - Duffus, R.L.
  - Dulles, Foster Rhea
  - Duveen, Joseph
  - Eaton, W.P.
  - Edel, Leon
  - Eden, Anthony, Earl of Avon
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David
  - Eisenhower, Mamie
  - Eisenhower, Milton S.
  - Erskine, John
  - Evans, Ernestine
  - Farrand, Beatrix
  - Farley, James A.
  - Farrar, John
  - Farrell, James T.
  - Fast, Howard
  - Ferber, Edna
  - Finley, John Huston
  - Fish, Hamilton, Jr.
  - Fish, Stuyvesant
  - Fisher, Dorothy Canfield
  - Flexner, Abraham
  - Foote, Shelby
  - Ford, Worthington C.
  - Frankfurter, Felix
  - Franke, William Birrell
  - Franklin, Fabian
  - Franklin, Margaret Ladd
  - Frost, Robert
  - Galbraith, John Kenneth
  - Gannett, lewis
  - Ghent, William James
  - Gibbs, Norman H.
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia C.
  - Green, Paul
  - Grew, Joseph C.
  - Hand, Learned
  - Hansen, Harry
  - Harriman, Averell
  - Harriman, Mary H.
  - Harriman, W.R.
  - Hazlitt, Henry
  - Hellman, Dillian
  - Henderson, Archibald
  - Herring, Pendleton
  - Hersey, John
  - Heubsch, Ben W.
  - Hicks, Cranville
  - Hill, Frank Ernest
  - Hillyer, Robert
  - Holt
  - Henry
  - Hoover, Herbert
  - House, Edward Mandell
  - Howe, M.A. DeWolfe
  - Hughes, Charles Evans
  - Hulbert, Murray
  - Hull, Cordell
  - Humphrey, Hubert H.
  - Hutchins, Robert
  - Husley, Julian
  - Irwin, Will
  - Isaacs, Stanley M.
  - Ives, Irving N.
  - Joad, C.E.M.
  - Johnson, Lyndon Baines
  - Johnson, Robert Underwood
  - Johnston, Eric
  - Jones, Howard Mumford
  - Josephson, Matthew
  - Jusserand, Jean Adrien Antione Jules
  - Kalternborn, Hans V.
  - Kazin, Alfred
  - Kellogg, Vernon Lyman
  - Kennan, George
  - Kennedy Ethel Skakel (Mrs. Robert F.)
  - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald
  - Kennedy, Joseph P.
  - Kennedy, Robert Francis
  - Keynes, John Maynard
  - Knight, Goodwin J.
  - Knollenberg, Bernhard
  - Knoof, Alfred A.
  - Knopf, Blanche W.
  - Komroff, Manuel
  - Krock, Arthur
  - Krutch, Joseph Wood
  - Kuchel, Thomas H.
  - Kandon, Alf M.
  - La Farge, Oliver
  - La Follette, Fola
  - Lasky, Melvin J.
  - Leach, Margaret Kernochan
  - Lehman, Edith Altschul
  - Lehman, Herbert H.
  - Lerner, Max
  - Lilienthal, David E.
  - Lindbergh, Charles A.
  - Lippman, Walter
  - Liverright, Horace B.
  - Longone, Pierre
  - Lord, Chester S.
  - Lovemann, Amy
  - Low, Will H.
  - Lowell, Amy
  - Lowell, Robert
  - McClure, Samuel Sidney
  - MacLeish, Archibald M.
  - Macmillan, Harold
  - Masters, Edgar Lee
  - Matthews, Brander
  - McCutcheon, John T.
  - McFee, William
  - Menninger, Karl
  - Meyner, Robert B.
  - Moore, Douglas
  - Moore, Marianne C.
  - Moore, Merill
  - More, Paul E.
  - Morgan, J. Pierpont
  - Morgenthau, Henry, Jr.
  - Morison, Samuel Eliot
  - Morley, Christopher
  - Morley, Frank Vigor
  - Murrow, Edward R.
  - Myers, Gustavus
  - Nathan, Robert
  - Neuberger, Richard
  - Newton, A. Edward
  - Nicolay, Helen
  - Niebuhr, Reinhold
  - Nixon, Thelma Catherine Ryan (Mrs. Richard Mulhouse)
  - Nock, Albert Jay
  - North, Sterling
  - O'Connor, Flannery
  - Ogden, Rollo
  - Orton, Vrest
  - Overton, Grant
  - Parsons, Geoffrey
  - Pepper, George Wharton
  - Perkins, Dexter
  - Perkins, Frances
  - Perkins, Maxwell E.
  - Piston, Walter
  - Prendergast, William A.
  - Pulitzer, Joseph
  - Putnam, George Haven
  - Ransom, John Crowe
  - Roberts, Kenneth
  - Rockefeller, David
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr.
  - Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano
  - Roosevelt, Mr. & Mrs. Franklin Delano
  - Roosevelt, Nicholas
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr.
  - Root, Elihu
  - Rothermere, Esmond Cecil Harmsworth, 2nd Viscount of Hemstead
  - Rowse, Alfred Leslie
  - Sadlair, Michael E.
  - Sandburg, Carl
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M.
  - Schlesinger, Arthur, Jr.
  - Schulberg, Budd
  - Schwengel, Fred Delbert
  - Seldes, Gilbert
  - Sessions, Roger
  - Seymour, Charles
  - Sherman, Stuart P.
  - Sherwood, Robert E.
  - Shotwell, James T.
  - Sinclair, Upton
  - Sitwell, Edith
  - Smith, Margaret Chase
  - Sorensen, Theodore C.
  - Stefanson, Vilhjalmur
  - Steffens, Lincoln
  - Stevens, Roger
  - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing
  - Stone, Irving
  - Stout, Rex
  - Street, Julian
  - Sullivan, Mark
  - Sulzberger, Arthur Hays
  - Taft, Henry W.
  - Taft, Robert A.
  - Tarbell, Ida M.
  - Tawney, Richard Henry
  - Teasdale, Sara
  - Thomas, Lowell
  - Thomas, Norman
  - Thorndike, Ashley Horace
  - Towne, Charles Hanson
  - Toynbee, Arnold Joseph
  - Trevelyan, George Macaulay
  - Trilling, Lionel
  - Truman, Harry S.
  - Turner, Frederick J.
  - Untermeyer, Louis
  - Van Doren, Carl
  - Van Doren, Irita
  - Van Doren, Mark
  - Van Dyke, Henry
  - Van Loon, Hendrik Willem
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison
  - Wagner Robert F.
  - Wallace, Henry Agard
  - Wallace, Irving
  - Walling, Anna Strunsky
  - Warde, Beatrice L.
  - Warren, Robert Penn
  - Webb, Walter Prescott
  - Wedgwood, Josiah Clement
  - Welles, Sumner
  - Wescott, Glenway
  - Wheelock, John Hall
  - White, Sallie L.
  - White, William Allen
  - Wickard, Claude R.
  - Wilson, Edmund
  - Winter, Ella (Mrs. Lincoln Steffens)
  - Winterick, John T.
  - Wyeth, Andrew
  - Yarboroug, Ralph W.
  - Young, Stark
  - Books
- Series III: Manuscripts, Diaries etc.
  - Manuscripts (Box 7)
  - Whitlock, Brand Diaries, Vols. 1-13, 1915-Jan. 1918 (Box 8)
    [8]
  - Whitlock, Brand Diaries, Vols. l4-25, Feb. l915-1921 (Box 9)
    [9]
  - Fish, Hamilton Diplomatic Crafts: Instruction and notes, Vol. I: Argentina - Italy, March 5, 1873-June 30, 1874 (Box 10)
    [10]
  - Fish, Hamilton Diplomatic Crafts: Instruction and notes, Vol. 2: Spain - Venezuela, July 1, 1874-October 31, 1876 (Box 11)
    [11]
  - Harry Truman Memoirs, Vols. 1-2 (Box 12)
    [12]
  - Harry Truman Memoirs, Vols. 3-4 (Box 13)
    [13]
  - Carl Sandburg Always the Young Strangers [advance mimeographed copy] (Box 14)
    [14]
  - Upton Sinclair Lanny Budd Rides Again [advance mimeographed copy] (Box 15)
    [15]
  - Brand Whitlock Misc. (Box 16)
    [16]
  - Misc. uncataloged: A.S. Hewitt; Peter Cooper; Cleveland, Grover; Chester, Arthur; William T. Coggeshall; Post Wheeler-Hallie E. Rivers Wedding Book (Box 17)
    [17]
  - Hone, Philip Memoirs, (3 loose volumes)
    [vols. 17, 18, 19 ]
  - Memoir and letters of George W. Strong to John N. Lloyd and miscellaneous letters from George W. Strong to and from others (than Mr. Lloyd) and from them to him, (1 looseleaf binder (loose))
  - Books
  - Strongbox of Brand Whitlock
  - 1 large soft-cover book entitled "Declaration of Independence - Evolution of the Text", Washington, D.C., Library of Congress, 1943
  - Diaries (Box 32)
  - Biographical and personal (contain some photographs) (Box 33 & 34b)
  - Oxford visit, 1965 (Box 34a & 34b)
  - National Book Award, [n.p.], 1971 (Given 13 Aprl 1972)
    [On top of diaries, Box 32]
  - Jose Rizal National Centennial Commission - Manila (Scrapbook of photos)
    [On top of Diaries, Box 32]
  - Transcript of essays for History and Historians with notes by Roy A. Billington, editor (Box 35)
    [Gift of Mrs. Allan Nevins]
  - Civil War Lectures (Box 36)
    [Gift, 1973]
  - Misc. Essays and Lectures (used by R.A. Billington) (Box 37)
  - Misc. notes and reflections: Articles, printed material and Manuscript of "The Free Negro in New York" (used by R.A. Billington) (Box 38)
  - Correspondence chronologically arranged, [v.p.], 1912-1975 (Box 39 - 80)
  - Correspondence Files (Box 81 & 82)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 83)
  - Subject Correspondence; letters to family; letters from A. Nevins (Box 84)
  - Adlai Stevenson Correspondence, James T. Farrell Correspondence, Subject Correspondence (Box 85)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box 86)
  - Civil War Centennial Commission (Box 87 & 88)
  - The American States During the Revolution: Notes and Manuscripts (Box 89 - 91)
  - The American States During and After the Revolution: Notes and Manuscripts (Box 92 & 93)
  - Ford Manuscript (Box 94)
  - Ford Biography (Box 95 - 100)
  - Cleveland (Box 101 - 105)
  - Cleveland Notes (Box 106)
  - Cleveland (Box 107)
  - Rockefeller Notes (Box 108-123)
  - 2 flat pictures (on top of above)
  - Scrapbook of clippings
  - Rockefeller Manuscript (Box 124-125)
  - Rockefeller notes (Box 126-133)
  - Standard Oil (Box 134-139)
  - Emergence of Lincoln notes (Box 140-148)
  - Ordeal of Union notes; Book reviews, 149 (Box 149-153)
  - Ordeal of the Union Manuscript (Box 154)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vol. 7 Ms. notes and drafts (Box 155)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vol. 7 Notes an Ms. (Chap. 9-13) (Box 156)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vols. 7 and 8 (Box 157-160)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vol. 8 Ms. (Box 161)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vol. 8 Misc. notes and drafts (Chap. 8-14) (Box 162)
  - Ordeal of the Union Vol. 8 Misc. notes and drafts (Chap. 1-7) (Box 163)
  - War for the Union Ms. (Box 164-165)
  - Civil War notes (Box 166-169)
  - Newspaper clippings on Civil War (Box 170)
  - Newspaper clippings on Civil War period (Box 171)
  - Civil War notes (Box 172)
  - Newspaper on Civil War (Box 173)
  - Gateway to History Manuscript (Box l74)
  - Fremont materials revised edition (proposed) 1973; Royalties,1927 ed. (Box 174-177)
  - Hamilton Fish materials (Box 178-179)
  - Nevins writings on Hamilton Fish (Box 181)
  - Hamilton Fish (Box 182)
  - Thos. J. Brady scrpbooks (Box 183-184)
  - Franklin Roosevelt scrapbooks (Box 185-186)
  - Printed materials by Nevins (Box 187)
  - Printed materials by and about Nevins [MICROFILM] (Box 188)
  - Misc. writings (Box 189-190)
  - James Truslow Adams material (Box 191-194)
  - Brand Whitlock materials (Box 195)
  - Grover Cleveland materials (Box 196)
  - Rockefeller materials (Box 197)
  - Dudley materials (Box 198)
  - Dissertations and writings by Nevins' students; List of CU students (Box 199-200)
  - Microfilm (Box 201)
  - Railroad notes: M.L. Daly's Union Democrat's Diary (Box 202)
  - Misc. notes, clippings, printed materials (Box 203)
  - Misc. unidentified manuscripts
  - Memorabilia (awards, certificates, degrees) (Box 204)
- Series IV: 1982 Gift
  Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, photographs, obituaries, memorials, and scrapbooks. Included are three letters from Van Wyck brooks and one letter from Willa Cather.